Guide to the Martin D. Hardin papers, 1881-1963
Hardin, Martin D. papers, 1881-1963
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Martin D. Hardin papers, 1881-1963, 1881-1946 (bulk).
329l
Martin D. Hardin, 1873-1935.
5 cubic ft.
Manuscript sermons, correspondence, a scrapbook, a manuscript, printed materials, and other items.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers of Martin D. Hardin, a Presbyterian clergyman, lecturer, and portrait artist. He seved as pastor of the First Presbyterian Church of Ithaca, New York, 1920-1935.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Martin D. Hardin was a Presbyterian clergyman, lecturer, and portrait artist. He seved as pastor of the First Presbyterian Church of Ithaca, New York, 1920-1935.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers consist primarily of manuscript sermons (1908-1935) by Hardin, including one preached at a memorial service (1914) for his father-in-law, U.S. Vice-President Adlai E. Stevenson. Also included is correspondence concerning his reasons for entering the ministry (1894), a call to the pastorate of the Second Presbyterian Church, Charlotte, N.C. (1903), his opinion concerning the views of William Jennings Bryan on evolution (1922), and life aboard the ocean liner Espagne during a voyage to Europe, where he was a lecturer for the American Red Cross (1918); correspondents include his father, Parker Watkins Hardin, his wife, Julia Stevenson Hardin, Joseph Quincy Adams, William C. Covert, Anna Camp Edwards, William T. Ellis, Parker C. Hardin, Arthur S. Hoyt, Duncan Campbell Lee, John B. Ross, Hoy W. Smith, Louis P. Smith, and John W. Stagg. Additional items include a scrapbook containing photographs of his portraits of Hugh A. Moran, Adlai E. Stevenson, Mynderse Van Cleef, Woodrow Wilson, and Roger B. Williams, an unpublished typescript (carbon) of "A Kentucky Hardin in the Ministry" written by Richard Henry Edwards, notes for an address broadcast from Glasgow, printed copies of sermons, and pamphlets.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hardin, Martin D., 1873-1935.; Adams, Joseph Quincy, 1881-1946.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Covert, William C.; Edwards, Anna Camp, 1876-1956.; Edwards, Richard Henry, 1877-1954.; Ellis, William T.; Hardin, Julia Stevenson.; Hardin, Parker C.; Hardin, Parker Watkins.; Hoyt, Arthur S.; Lee, Duncan Campbell.; Moran, Hugh A.; Ross, John B.; Smith, Hoy W.; Smith, Louis P.; Stagg, John W.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Van Cleef, Mynderse.; Williams, Roger B.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Espagne (ship); Red Cross.United States.American National Red Cross.; Second Presbyterian Church (Charlotte, N.C.).
Subjects:
Clergy.
Form and Genre Terms:
Sermons.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence
  - Martin to his father explaining why he is entering the ministry (photocopy), May 4, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Julia Stevenson Hardin to her parents, Aug. 1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to his mother-in-law, Mrs. Adlai E. Stevenson, Aug. 13, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Julia Hardin and Martin to her parents, Aug. 26, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Julia Hardin to Martin, July 2, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - John B. Ross, chairman of the Advisory Committee on Pastorate of the Second Presbyterian Church, Charlotte, N.C., informing Martin of his call to their pastorate, July 22, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - John W. Stagg, pastor of First Presbyterian Church, Birmingham, Alabama, urging Martin to accept the call to Charlotte, July 22, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to Julia, ca. 1908 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to Julia, Jan. 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to Julia, Feb. 23, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to Julia, Mar. 17, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to daughter Laetitia at Vassar, ca. 1916-1918, Jan. 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to Julia, Mar. 10, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to Julia, Mar. 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to William Jennings Bryan opposing Bryan's articles in evolution, Mar. 16, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arthur S. Hoyt re: Bryan, Apr. 27, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - William Thomas Ellis re: Martin's address, "Mr. Bryan and Evolution", May 3, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - LPS (Louis P. Smith) to Julius Steele, Kenwood Church, Chicago, recommending Martin as Churchman, Rotarian, and American (photostat of a carbon), Oct. 27, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to daughter "Blessed Girlie", Jan. 31, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to daughter Julia at Emma Willard School, Oct. 4, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to daughter Julia, Nov. 5, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to daughter Julia, May 17, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hoy Watson Smith, Second Presbyterian Church, Little Rock, Ark. re: a letter written in 1903 by Dr. Walter W. Moore to Dr. Alexander McKelway, Aug. 3, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to wife Julia, ca. 1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Joseph Quincy Adams, The Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C., Nov. 13, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anna P. Edwards to Julia, Dec. 15, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - John Timothy Stone to Julia, Dec. 16, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Duncan Campbell Lee to Julia, Jan. 2, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Parker Calhoun Hardin to his mother, Julia, ca. 1938, Apr. 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Martin to Adlai E. Stevenson about his (Martin's) visit to Charlotte and of speakers for the Sunday Evening Club (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Frank Graham, United Nations, to Judy Hardin Baumgarten re: biographical material of her father (photocopy), Apr. 19, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Small notebook of sketches, (pencil, pen-and-ink, and watercolor) by Martin, age 7 1/2, Jan. 1881 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carbon typescript, two pages 18 and 26; speech or sermon re: World War I in Europe - possibly lecture for Red Cross, ca. 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notes for broadcast address from Glasgow on Sunday, May 22, 1927, by Martin; subject, The Modern Man's Neighbor (typescript) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Passport; includes photograph of Martin and Julia, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Prayer on Memorial Day, in memory of Martin (carbon typescript), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newsclipping from Ithaca Journal; illustration and short article about portrait of Roger B. Williams, painted by Martin, Jan. 3, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carbon typescript of "Mr. Bryan, Martin Hardin and the Moderatorship of the Presbyterian General Assembly," signed by Hugh Moran, Palo Alto, Cal., Nov. 24, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook of photographs of paintings mostly made from photographs by Martin; includes Woodrow Wilson, Vice President Adlai Ewing Stevenson, Mrs. Richard Edwards, Roger B. Williams, Hugh A. Moran, Mynderse Van Cleef (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mss. volume: "A Kentucky Hardin in the Ministry" by Richard Henry Edwards; this is a carbon typescript of unpublished manuscript written "to perpetuate the memory..." of Martin, ca. 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Manuscript sermons
  - 1908-1912 (Box 2)
  - 1913-1914 (Box 3)
  - 1915-1920 (Box 4)
  - 1920-1922 (Box 5)
  - 1922-1923 (Box 6)
  - 1924-1925 (Box 7)
  - 1926-1927 (Box 8)
  - 1928-1929 (Box 9)
  - 1930-1931 (Box 10)
  - 1932-1935, and printed material: sermonds, church publications, 1908-1927, 1940 (Box 11)
  - undated (Box 12-24)